here's a problem from a 1976 Journal of
recreational mathematics issue that
Roger Nelson calls the Christmas tree
problem start with a circle and inside
the circle inscribe an isoceles triangle
along the diameter like this inside of
the isoceles triangle let's inscribe a
circle the bottom radius shown bcts the
diameter we can use the two quadrants
created to inscribe two more circles
like
this the the problem in the journal asks
you to prove that these three small
inscribed circles are all congruent
pause the video and think about this
before I reveal one possible
answer are you ready to see a solution
it turns out that we can prove this fact
visually by changing our point of view
we take a second copy of the Outer
Circle and shift it up by a distance
equal to the radius then rotate 45° or <
over 4 radians from this perspective we
see that the top circle inscribed in the
triangle is actually one of the pair of
the two circles inscribed in the two
quadrants of this new Circle therefore
these two circles are congruent to the
original two in the bottom quadrant of
the original Circle and this means that
all three of the original inscribed
small circles are congruent to one
another thanks for watching if you like
this video and others on my channel you
might enjoy Roger Nelson's books proofs
without words there are three different
compendia Linked In the
description